     proc sql;
        create view sasuser.faview as
           select lastname, firstname, gender,
                  int((today()-dateofbirth)/365.25) as Age,
                  substr(jobcode,3,1) as Level,
                  salary
              from sasuser.payrollmaster,
                   sasuser.staffmaster


Guidelines for Using PROC SQL Views

Avoid using an ORDER BY clause in a view definition, which causes the data to be sorted every time the view is executed. Users of the view might differ in how or whether they want the data to be sorted, so it is more efficient to specify an ORDER BY clause in a query that references the view.

If the same data is used many times in one program or in multiple programs, it is more efficient to create a table rather than a view because the data must be accessed at each view reference. (This table can be a temporary table in the Work library.)

Avoid creating views that are based on tables whose structure might change. A view is no longer valid when it references a nonexistent column.

Dynamic change view access

     libname airline 'SAS-library one';
     proc sql;
        create view sasuser.payrollv as
           select*
              from airline.payrollmaster
              using libname airline 'SAS-library two';
     quit;
     proc print data=sasuser.payrollv;
     run;

proc sql;
   create view data.state as
      select name as County,
             population/area as Density
         from state.data;

CANNOT update Density(derived)!!!!