select a default page size：BUFSIZE= ，reduce I/0
small dataset more bufno less I/O
Both with options

To reduce I/O operations on a small data set, allocate as many buffers as there are pages in the data set so that the entire data set can be loaded into memory. This technique is most effective if you read the same observations several times during processing.

Under the z/OS operating environment, as the size of the data set increases, increase the number of buffers allocated, rather than the size of each buffer, to minimize I/O consumption.

The product of BUFNO= and BUFSIZE=, rather than the specific value of either option, determines how much data can be transferred in one I/O operation.

sasfile company.sales load; 
load data in memory avoid I/O
sasfile company.sales close;

If you need to repeatedly process a SAS data file that will fit entirely in memory, use the SASFILE statement to reduce I/O and some CPU usage.

If you use the SASFILE statement and the SAS data file will not fit entirely in memory, the code will execute, but there might be a degradation in performance.

If you need to repeatedly process part of a SAS data file and the entire file won't fit into memory, use a DATA step with the SASFILE statement to create a subset of the file that does fit into memory, and then process that subset repeatedly. This saves CPU time in the processing steps because those steps will read a smaller file, in addition to the benefit of the file being resident in memory.

use the IBUFSIZE= system option to specify the page size for an index file