A BY statement does not use an index if the BY statement includes the DESCENDING or NOTSORTED option or if SAS detects that the data file is physically stored in sorted order on the BY variables.

To conserve resources, use sort order rather than an index for BY-group processing.
cannot use by if not indexed or sorted

The NOTSORTED option specifies that observations that have the same BY value are grouped together but are not necessarily sorted in alphabetical or numeric order.

The NOTSORTED option cannot be used with the MERGE or UPDATE statements.


By creating a format for the data and using the GROUPFORMAT and NOTSORTED options, you cause SAS to create the variables FIRST.Order_Date and LAST.Order_Date based on the formatted values, not the internal values

proc format;
        value qtrfmt '01jan2002' d - '31mar2002' d = '1'
                     '01apr2002' d - '30jun2002' d = '2'
                     '01jul2002' d - '30sep2002' d = '3' 
                     '01oct2002' d - '31dec2002' d = '4';
     run;         
     data company.quarters(keep=count order_date
                rename=(order_date=Quarter));
        set retail.orders;
        format order_date qtrfmt.;
        by  order_date groupformat notsorted;
        where year(order_date)=2002;
        if first.order_date then Count=0;
        Count +1;
        if last.order_date;
      run;

the CLASS statement does not require the data to be presorted using the CLASS values, nor does it require an index that is based on the CLASS variables.

If you can presort the data, use just a BY statement rather than a CLASS statement or a BY statement with a separate SORT procedure.

If you cannot sort the data, use the CLASS statement.

Do not presort the data for use with a CLASS statement. Presorting the data does not provide a significant benefit.

a small SORTSIZE= value can increase CPU and I/O resource utilization
a large SORTSIZE= value can decrease CPU and I/O resource utilization.

Use a DATA step rather than PROC APPEND to re-create a large data set from smaller subsets. 

Use a constant rather than a SAS function because calling a function repeatedly increases CPU usage.

Use a subsetting IF with either a constant or a function rather than a WHERE statement with a function.

The NODUPKEY option checks for and eliminates observations that have duplicate BY-variable values

     proc sort data=company.reorder nodupkey;
        by product_line product_name;
     run;

 the NODUPRECS option compares all of the variable values for each observation to those for the previous observation that was written to the output data set. If an exact match is found, then the observation is not written to the output data set.

     proc sort data=company.reorder noduprecs;
        by product_line;
     run;

EQUALS | NOEQUALS is a SORT procedure option that helps to determine the order of observations in the output data set. When you use NODUPRECS or NODUPKEY to remove observations from the output data set, the choice of EQUALS or NOEQUALS can have an effect on which observations are removed.

EQUALS is the default. For observations that have identical BY-variable values, EQUALS maintains the order from the input data set in the output data set. NOEQUALS does not necessarily preserve this order in the output data set. NOEQUALS can save CPU time and memory resources.

To remove duplicate observations from a SAS data set, use PROC SORT with the NODUPKEY option rather than a PROC SORT step followed by a DATA step that uses FIRST. processing.