%include 'c:\mylib\sample.sas';
SOURCE2 option if you want the contents of the file to be written to the SAS log.
	
 
Using the Autocall Facility
OPTIONS MAUTOSOURCE | NOMAUTOSOURCE;
MAUTOSOURCE is the default setting, and specifies that the autocall facility is available
NOMAUTOSOURCE specifies that the autocall facility is not available.


The SASAUTOS system option controls where the macro facility looks for autocall macros.
    options mautosource sasautos=('c:\mysasfiles',sasautos);
    %prtlast

The Stored Compiled Macro Facility
	libname macrolib 'c:\storedlib';
     options mstored sasmstore=macrolib;

     %macro words(text,root=w,delim=%str( ))/store;
        %local i word;
        %let i=1;
        %let word=%scan(&text,&i,&delim);

The MSTORED option determines whether the Stored Compiled Macro Facility is available. The SASMSTORE option controls where the macro facility looks for stored compiled macros.

The Stored Compiled Macro Facility can be used in conjunction with the Autocall Facility and with session-compiled macros. When you submit a macro call such as %words, the macro processor searches for the macro Words as

an entry named Words.Macro in the temporary Work.Sasmacr catalog.

an entry named Words.Macro in the Libref.Sasmacr catalog. The MSTORED option must be specified, and the SASMSTORE option must have a value of Libref.

an autocall library member named Words that contains the macro definition for the macro Words. The MAUTOSOURCE option must be specified, and the value of the SASAUTOS option must point to the autocall library.

The macro processor checks the temporary catalog Work.Sasmacr first. If the macro is not found there, the macro processor looks in the permanent Sasmacr catalog, if one has been specified. Finally, the macro processor checks the autocall library.