*when you use two periods, the macro variable 
references in your program resolve correctly.;


     %let yr=1999;
     %let period=end;
     %let libref=hrd;
     title "Temporary Employees for &yr";
     data &libref..temp&yr;
        set &libref..temp;
        if year(&period.date)=&yr;
     run;
     proc print data=&libref..temp&yr;
     run;

data &libref..temp&yr;
data hrd.temp1999;

*produce macro when exe,call symput;

     data hrd.overtime;
        set hrd.temp(keep=name overtime);
        if overtime ne .;
        TotalOvertime+overtime;
        call symput('total',put(totalovertime,2.));
     run;
     title "Temporary Employees Worked &total Overtime Hours";
     proc print data=hrd.overtime;
     run;

*input control @9 before var;
input LastName $7. @9 FirstName $5.
input @9 FirstName $5. @1 LastName $7. +7 JobTitle 3.;
infile receipts pad;
*DEBUG: pad option The PAD option is useful only when missing data occurs at the end of a record and when SAS encounters an end-of-record marker before the last field is completely read.;
*DEBUG: 
The default value of the maximum record length is determined by your operating system. If you get unexpected results when reading many variables, you might need to change the maximum record length by specifying the LRECL=option in the INFILE statement. For more information about the LRECL= option, see the SAS documentation for your operating environment.;